### Héctor Climente González

## Computational biologist & machine learning researcher

# ✓ Kyoto, Japan +34 6 44 33 64 19 □ https://hclimente.eu in linkedin.com/in/hclimente

#### ABOUT ME

"Learn only to be content" - Inscription in Ryōan-ji, Kyōto.

After four years of experience in bioinformatics, I closed the gap in mathematical skills and pursued a career as a machine learning scientist. In my research, I develop new machine learning algorithms to improve our understanding of biology.

The driving forces of my life are learning and personal growth. I strongly believe in multidisciplinarity and collaboration, and in creating synergies between engineering and fundamental research, biology and machine learning, academia and the private sector.

#### SELECTED WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Postdoctoral researcher

MAY 2020 - NOW

#### RIKEN AIP

- ▶ Developed machine learning methods for biological problems, including graph-based and deep learning algorithms
- ▶Applied the algorithms above to discover new drug targets of leukemia (RNA-seq data) and breast cancer (imaging data)

#### Doctoral researcher

OCT 2016 - APR 2020

Institut Curie & Mines Paris Tech

- ▶ Developed machine learning methods that leverage prior biological knowledge to study the genetics of complex diseases
- ▶ Applied the algorithms above to GWAS, to find both single-SNP associations and epistasis
- ▶ Authored an R package *martini* published in Bioconductor, and two Python packages, *pyHSICLasso* and *spada* in PyPI

#### Research assistant

DEC 2013 - AUG 2016

Pompeu Fabra University

▶ Conducted a highly-cited study on the functional implications of alternative splicing in cancer

#### Head of Biocomputing

SEP 2014 - MAY 2015

Anaxomics Biotech Ltd.

- ▶ Coordinated the company's bioinformatics activities, including decision-making, supervising an intern, and collaboration with IT to maintain the database and the framework
- ▶ Developed and maintained pipelines for the statistical analysis of bulk RNA-seq, microarray, WGS and MS/MS data

#### **EDUCATION**

2016 – 2020 **Ph.D. in Bioinformatics**Paris Sciences & Lettres Univ.

2012 – 2014 M.Sc. in Bioinformatics

GPA 9/10

Pompeu Fabra University

2010 – 2013 **B.Sc. in Biochemistry** 

GPA 8.74/10, 1<sup>st</sup> Class Honors *Barcelona Autonomous Univ.* 

2008 – 2012 **B.Sc. in Biotechnology** 

GPA 8.58/10

Barcelona Autonomous Univ.

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Co-author of 10 articles, cited over 500 times.

Climente-González et al. (2020). Boosting GWAS using biological networks: a study on susceptibility to familial breast cancer. PLoS Comp Bio, 17 (3)

Climente-González et al. (2019). Block HSIC Lasso: model-free biomarker detection for ultra-high dimensional data. *Bioinformatics*, 35 (15), i427–i435.

Climente-González et al. (2017). The functional impact of alternative splicing in cancer. Cell reports, 20 (9), 2215-2226.

#### SELECTED AWARDS

2020 Special Postdoc. Researcher

RIKEN

2016 – 2019 **PhD EU Fellowship** 

MSCA COFUND

#### LANGUAGES

SPANISH Native ENGLISH Fluent

FRENCH Intermediate

JAPANESE Beginner

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

PROGRAMMING Python, R, C++, Bash

PYTHON pytorch, numpy, pandas, scikit-learn

R tidyverse, igraph, Rcpp

BIG DATA nextflow, HPC (PBS Torque, Slurm),

SQL, Jupyter

OMICS GWAS, RNA-Seq (single cell and bulk),

MS-MS proteomics

ML/STATISTICS Graph regularization, statistical

interactions, nonlinear association

deep learning

DEVOPS Docker, conda, unit testing, continuous

integration, git

#### **SOFT SKILLS**

- ▶ Courses on the **mathematics** and **engineering** of machine learning: deep learning, probability and statistics.
- ▶ Experienced **communicator**: talks in international conferences, lead writer of articles and grant proposals, workshop instructor on reproducible research
- ▶ **Project management** in teams and singleperson projects, **mentoring**, and coordination of **international collaborations**
- ▶ **Organization** of summer school on breast cancer, **teaching** assistant in large scale machine learning course
- Courses on critical thinking, ethics, project management, theater, and mindfulness